<?xml version="1.0" encoding="US-ASCII"?>

<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "rfc2629.dtd">
<?xml-stylesheet type='text/xsl' href='rfc2629.xslt' ?>

<?rfc strict="yes" ?>
<?rfc toc="yes"?>
<?rfc tocdepth="4"?>
<?rfc symrefs="yes"?>
<?rfc sortrefs="yes" ?>
<?rfc compact="yes" ?>
<?rfc subcompact="no" ?>

<rfc category="std" number="8476" ipr="trust200902"
     submissionType="IETF" consensus="yes">

  <front>
    <title abbrev="Signaling MSD Using OSPF">Signaling Maximum SID Depth (MSD) Using OSPF</title>

      <author fullname="Jeff Tantsura" initials="J.T." surname="Tantsura">
      <organization>Apstra, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>jefftant.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Uma Chunduri" initials="U.C." surname="Chunduri">
      <organization>Huawei Technologies</organization>
      <address>
      <email>uma.chunduri@huawei.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

   <author fullname="Sam Aldrin" initials="S.A." surname="Aldrin">
      <organization>Google, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>aldrin.ietf@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <author fullname="Peter Psenak" initials="P.P." surname="Psenak">
      <organization>Cisco Systems</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ppsenak@cisco.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>

    <date month="December" year="2018" />

    <keyword>BGP-LS</keyword>
    <keyword>SID</keyword>
    <keyword>MSD</keyword>
    <keyword>OSPF</keyword>

   <abstract>
        <t>This document defines a way for an Open Shortest Path First (OSPF)
 router to advertise multiple
        types of supported Maximum SID Depths (MSDs) at node and/or link
        granularity. Such advertisements allow entities (e.g., centralized
        controllers) to determine whether a particular Segment
   Identifier (SID) stack can be supported
        in a given network. This document only refers to the Signaling MSD as
	defined in RFC 8491, but it defines an encoding that can support
        other MSD types. Here, the term "OSPF" means both OSPFv2 and OSPFv3.
        </t>

    </abstract>
  </front>

  <middle>
          <section title="Introduction">
      <t>When Segment Routing (SR) paths are computed by a centralized
      controller, it is critical that the controller learn the Maximum SID 
      Depth (MSD) that can be imposed at each node/link on a given SR path.
      This ensures that the Segment Identifier (SID) stack depth of a computed
      path doesn't exceed the number of SIDs the node is capable of
      imposing.</t>

      <t><xref target="PCEP-EXT"/> defines how to signal MSD in the
      Path Computation Element Communication Protocol (PCEP). However, if PCEP
      is not supported/configured on the head-end of an SR tunnel or a
      Binding-SID anchor node, and the controller does not participate in IGP
      routing, it has no way of learning the MSD of nodes and
      links. BGP&nbhy;LS (Distribution of Link-State and TE Information Using
      BGP) <xref target="RFC7752"/> defines a way to
      expose topology and associated attributes and capabilities of the nodes
      in that topology to a centralized controller. MSD signaling by BGP-LS
      has been defined in <xref target="MSD-BGP"/>. Typically, BGP-LS is
      configured on a small number of nodes that do not necessarily act as
      head-ends. In order for BGP-LS to signal MSD for all the nodes and links
      in the network for which MSD is relevant, MSD capabilities SHOULD be
      advertised by every OSPF router in the network.</t>

      <t>Other types of MSDs are known to be useful. For example,
      <xref target="ELC-ISIS"/> defines Entropy Readable Label Depth (ERLD),
      which is used by a head&nbhy;end to insert an Entropy Label (EL) at a
      depth where it can be read by transit nodes.</t>

      <t>This document defines an extension to OSPF used to advertise one or
      more types of MSDs at node and/or link granularity.
      In the future, it is expected that new MSD-Types will be defined to
      signal additional capabilities, e.g., ELs, SIDs that can be
      imposed through recirculation, or SIDs associated with another data
      plane such as IPv6. </t>

      <t>MSD advertisements MAY be useful even if SR itself is
      not enabled. For example, in a non-SR MPLS network, MSD defines the
      maximum label depth.</t>

        <section title="Terminology">

  <t>This memo makes use of the terms defined in <xref target="RFC7770"/>.</t>

<t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="9">
    <t hangText="BGP-LS:">Distribution of Link-State and TE Information Using
    BGP</t>

    <t hangText="OSPF:">Open Shortest Path First</t>

    <t hangText="MSD:">Maximum SID Depth - the number of SIDs supported by a
    node or a link on a node</t>

    <t hangText="SID:">Segment Identifier as defined in <xref
    target="RFC8402"/></t>

    <t hangText="Label Imposition:">Imposition is the act of modifying and/or
    adding labels to the outgoing label stack associated with a packet. This
    includes:

        <list style="symbols">
            <t>replacing the label at the top of the label stack with a new
            label</t>

            <t>pushing one or more new labels onto the label stack</t>
        </list></t></list></t>

    <t>The number of labels imposed is then the sum of the number of
    labels that are replaced and the number of labels that are
    pushed.  See <xref target="RFC3031"/> for further details.</t>

   <t><list style="hanging" hangIndent="9">
        <t hangText="PCEP:">Path Computation Element Communication Protocol</t>

        <t hangText="SR:">Segment Routing</t>

        <t hangText="LSA:">Link State Advertisement</t>

        <t hangText="RI:">Router Information</t>
      </list></t>

        </section>

        <section title="Requirements Language">
        <t>The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL",
        "SHALL&nbsp;NOT", "SHOULD", "SHOULD&nbsp;NOT", "RECOMMENDED",
        "NOT&nbsp;RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this document
        are to be interpreted as described in BCP&nbsp;14
        <xref target="RFC2119"/> <xref target="RFC8174"/> when,
        and only when, they appear in all capitals, as shown here.</t>
    </section>
    </section>
    <section anchor="NODE_LEVEL" title="Node MSD Advertisement">
      <t>The Node MSD TLV within the body of the OSPF RI Opaque LSA <xref
      target="RFC7770"/> is defined to carry the provisioned SID depth of the
      router originating the RI LSA. Node MSD is the smallest MSD supported
      by the node on the set of interfaces configured for use by the
      advertising IGP instance. MSD values may be learned via a hardware API
      or may be provisioned.
      </t>
      <figure align="center" anchor="Node_MSD_TLV"
              title="Node MSD TLV">
          <artwork align="left">
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |    Type                       |  Length                       |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |    MSD-Type   |  MSD-Value    |  MSD-Type...  |  MSD-Value... | 
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          </artwork>
  </figure>

      <t>Type: 12</t>
      <t>Length: variable (multiple of 2 octets); represents the total
      length of the value field in octets.</t>
      <t>Value: consists of one or more pairs of a 1&nbhy;octet MSD-Type and
      1&nbhy;octet MSD-Value.</t>
      <t>MSD-Type: one of the values defined in the "IGP MSD-Types" registry
      defined in <xref target="RFC8491"/>.</t>
      <t>MSD-Value: a number in the range of 0-255. For all MSD-Types, 0
      represents the lack of ability to impose an MSD stack of any depth; any
      other value represents that of the node. This value MUST represent the
      lowest value supported by any link configured for use by the advertising
      OSPF instance.</t>
      <t>This TLV is optional and is applicable to both OSPFv2 and OSPFv3.
      The scope of the advertisement is specific to the deployment.</t>
         
      <t>When multiple Node MSD TLVs are received from a given router, the
        receiver MUST use the first occurrence of the TLV in the Router
        Information (RI) LSA.  If the Node MSD TLV appears in multiple RI
        LSAs that have different flooding scopes, the Node
        MSD TLV in the RI LSA with the area-scoped
        flooding scope MUST be used.  If the Node MSD TLV appears in
        multiple RI LSAs that have the same flooding scope,
        the Node MSD TLV in the RI LSA with the
        numerically smallest Instance ID MUST be used and other
        instances of the Node MSD TLV MUST be ignored.
 
        The RI LSA can be advertised at any of the defined opaque flooding
        scopes (link, area, or Autonomous System (AS)).  For the purpose of
        Node MSD TLV advertisement, area-scoped flooding is RECOMMENDED. </t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="LINK_LEVEL" title="Link MSD Sub-TLV">
      <t>The Link MSD sub-TLV is defined to carry the MSD of the interface
      associated with the link. MSD values may be learned via a hardware API
      or may be provisioned.</t>

    <figure align="center" anchor="Link_MSD_sub_TLV"
              title="Link MSD Sub-TLV">
          <artwork align="left">
   0                   1                   2                   3
   0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1 2 3 4 5 6 7 8 9 0 1
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |    Type                       |  Length                       |
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
  |    MSD-Type   |  MSD-Value    |  MSD-Type...  |  MSD-Value... | 
  +-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+-+
          </artwork>
  </figure>

  <t>Type:</t>
  <t><list> 
     <t>For OSPFv2, the link-level MSD-Value is advertised as an
     optional sub-TLV of the OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV as defined in
     <xref target="RFC7684"/> and has a type of 6.</t>
     <t>For OSPFv3, the link-level MSD-Value is advertised as an
     optional sub-TLV of the E-Router-LSA TLV as defined in <xref
     target="RFC8362"/> and has a type of 9.
     </t>
   </list></t>
  <t>Length: variable; same as defined in <xref target="NODE_LEVEL">
  </xref>.</t>
  <t>Value: consists of one or more pairs of a 1&nbhy;octet MSD-Type and
  1&nbhy;octet MSD-Value. </t>

  <t>MSD-Type: one of the values defined in the "IGP MSD-Types" registry
  defined in <xref target="RFC8491"/>.</t> 
  <t>The MSD-Value field contains the Link MSD of the router originating
  the corresponding LSA as specified for OSPFv2 and OSPFv3.  The Link MSD
  is a number in the range of 0-255. For all MSD-Types, 0 represents the
  lack of ability to impose an MSD stack of any depth; any other value
  represents that of the particular link when used as an outgoing
  interface.</t>

  <t>
  If this sub-TLV is advertised multiple times for the same link in
  different OSPF Extended Link Opaque LSAs / E-Router-LSAs originated
  by the same OSPF router, the sub-TLV in the OSPFv2 Extended Link
  Opaque LSA with the smallest Opaque ID or in the OSPFv3
  E-Router-LSA with the smallest Link State ID MUST be used by
  receiving OSPF routers.  This situation SHOULD be logged as an error.
  </t>

             </section>

             <section anchor="Confict_resolution"
             title="Procedures for Defining and Using Node and Link MSD Advertisements">
      <t>When Link MSD is present for a given MSD-Type, the value of the Link
      MSD MUST take precedence over the Node MSD. When a Link MSD&nbhy;Type
      is not signaled but the Node MSD-Type is, then the Node MSD&nbhy;Type
      value MUST be considered as the MSD value for that link.</t>

      <t>In order to increase flooding efficiency, it is RECOMMENDED that
      routers with homogenous Link MSD values advertise just the Node MSD
      value.</t>

      <t>The meaning of the absence of both Node and Link MSD advertisements
      for a given MSD-Type is specific to the MSD-Type. Generally, it can only
      be inferred that the advertising node does not support advertisement of
      that MSD-Type. However, in some cases the lack of advertisement might
      imply that the functionality associated with the MSD-Type is not
      supported. Per <xref target="RFC8491"/>, the correct interpretation MUST
      be specified when an MSD-Type is defined.</t>

    </section>

    <section anchor="IANA" title="IANA Considerations">
    <t>This specification updates several existing OSPF registries.</t>
      <t>IANA has allocated TLV type 12 from the "OSPF Router
      Information (RI) TLVs" registry as defined by <xref target="RFC7770"/>.

    <figure align="center" anchor="Node_MSD"
              title="RI Node MSD">
          <artwork align="left">
   Value     Description                      Reference
   -----     ---------------                  -------------
   12        Node MSD                         This document
          </artwork>
  </figure>

  IANA has allocated sub-TLV type 6 from
  the "OSPFv2 Extended Link TLV Sub-TLVs" registry.

  <figure align="center" anchor="OSPFv2_Link_MSD"
              title="OSPFv2 Link MSD">

          <artwork align="left">
   Value     Description                      Reference
   -----     ---------------                  -------------
   6         OSPFv2 Link MSD                  This document
          </artwork>
  </figure>

  IANA has allocated sub-TLV type 9 from the "OSPFv3 Extended-LSA
  Sub&nbhy;TLVs" registry.

  <figure align="center" anchor="OSPFv3_Link_MSD"
      title="OSPFv3 Link MSD">
  <artwork align="left">
   Value     Description                      Reference
   -----     ---------------                  -------------
   9         OSPFv3 Link MSD                  This document
          </artwork>
  </figure>
     </t>
</section>

  <section anchor="Security" title="Security Considerations">
    <t>Security concerns for OSPF are addressed in <xref target="RFC7474"/>,
    <xref target="RFC4552"/>, and <xref target="RFC7166"/>.
    Further security analysis for the OSPF protocol is done in <xref
    target="RFC6863"/>. Security considerations as specified by <xref
    target="RFC7770"/>, <xref target="RFC7684"/>, and <xref target="RFC8362"/>
    are applicable to this document.</t>

   <t>Implementations MUST ensure that malformed TLVs and sub-TLVs defined in
   this document are detected and do not provide a vulnerability for
   attackers to crash the OSPF router or routing process.  Reception
   of malformed TLVs or sub-TLVs SHOULD be counted and/or logged for
   further analysis.  Logging of malformed TLVs and sub-TLVs SHOULD be
   rate&nbhy;limited to prevent a Denial-of-Service (DoS) attack (distributed
   or otherwise) from overloading the OSPF control plane.</t>

   <t>Advertisement of an incorrect MSD value may have negative
   consequences. If the value is smaller than supported, path computation
   may fail to compute a viable path. If the value is larger than
   supported, an attempt to instantiate a path that can't be supported by
   the head-end (the node performing the SID imposition) may occur.</t>

   <t>The presence of this information may also inform an attacker of how
   to induce any of the aforementioned conditions.</t>

   <t>There's no DoS risk specific to this extension, and it is
   not vulnerable to replay attacks.</t>

                </section>

  </middle>

  <back>
    <references title="Normative References">
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.2119"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8174"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7770"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8362"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7684"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.3031"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8402"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.8491"?>
    </references>

    <references title="Informative References">

<!-- draft-ietf-pce-segment-routing (Waiting for Writeup) -->
<reference anchor='PCEP-EXT'>
<front>
<title>PCEP Extensions for Segment Routing</title>
<author initials='S' surname='Sivabalan' fullname='Siva Sivabalan'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Tantsura' fullname='Jeff Tantsura'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='W' surname='Henderickx' fullname='Wim Henderickx'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='J' surname='Hardwick' fullname='Jonathan Hardwick'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='October' year='2018' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-pce-segment-routing-14' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-idr-bgp-ls-segment-routing-msd (I-D Exists) -->
<reference anchor='MSD-BGP'>
<front>
<title>Signaling MSD (Maximum SID Depth) using Border Gateway Protocol Link-State</title>
<author initials='J' surname='Tantsura' fullname='Jeff Tantsura'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='U' surname='Chunduri' fullname='Uma Chunduri'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='G' surname='Mirsky' fullname='Gregory Mirsky'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Sivabalan' fullname='Siva Sivabalan'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='August' year='2018' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-idr-bgp-ls-segment-routing-msd-02' />
</reference>

<!-- draft-ietf-ospf-mpls-elc (I-D Exists) -->
<reference anchor='ELC-ISIS'>
<front>
<title>Signaling Entropy Label Capability and Entropy Readable Label-stack Depth Using OSPF</title>
<author initials='X' surname='Xu' fullname='Xiaohu Xu'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Kini' fullname='Sriganesh Kini'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Sivabalan' fullname='Siva Sivabalan'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='C' surname='Filsfils' fullname='Clarence Filsfils'>
    <organization />
</author>
<author initials='S' surname='Litkowski' fullname='Stephane Litkowski'>
    <organization />
</author>
<date month='September' year='2018' />
</front>
<seriesInfo name='Work in Progress,' value='draft-ietf-ospf-mpls-elc-07' />
</reference>

      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7752"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.6863"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7474"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.4552"?>
      <?rfc include="reference.RFC.7166"?>

    </references>

     <section anchor="Acknowledgements" title="Acknowledgements" numbered="no">
       <t>The authors would like to thank Acee Lindem, Ketan Talaulikar,
       Tal Mizrahi, Stephane Litkowski, and Bruno Decraene for their reviews
       and valuable comments.</t>
    </section>

        <section anchor="Contributors" title="Contributors" numbered="no">

             <t>The following person contributed to this document:</t>
             <t>Les Ginsberg</t>
             <t>Email: ginsberg@cisco.com</t>
    </section>

  </back>
</rfc>
